[
    {
        "question": "On þissum geare ferde seo (<em>micel</em>) #### scipfierd eft on Englalande⁠ — In this year the great navy went again to England",
        "correctAnswer": "micele",
        "explanation":"Here 'micel' is modifying the singular nominative feminine 'scipfierd' so it takes the feminine 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "micela",
                "explanation": "An adjective takes the gender of its noun. As can be seen by 'seo', 'scipfierd' is feminine so 'micel' should take the feminine nominative 'e' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>yfel</em>) #### unrihtwisa cyning spræc mid his yflan tungan⁠ — The evil unrighteous king spoke with his evil mouth",
        "correctAnswer": "yfela",
        "explanation":"Here 'yfel' is modifying the singular nominative masculine 'cyning' so it takes the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "yfele",
                "explanation": "An adjective takes the gender of its noun. As can be seen by 'se', 'cyning' is masculine so 'yfel' should take the masculine nominative 'a' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>swet</em>) #### mete ðe hie heton monna se him cuom of hefonum⁠ — The sweet meats that they call mana which comes from heaven",
        "correctAnswer": "sweta",
        "explanation":"Here 'swet' is modifying the singular nominative masculine 'mete' so it takes the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "swete",
                "explanation": "An adjective takes the gender of its noun. As can be seen by 'se', 'mete' is masculine so 'swet' should take the masculine nominative 'a' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Dol bið þæt (<em>lytel</em>) #### scip ðe gæð on deop wæter⁠ — Foolish is the little ship that goes in deep water",
        "correctAnswer": "lytle",
        "explanation":"Here 'lytel' is modifying the singular nominative neuter 'scip' so it takes the neuter 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "lytele",
                "explanation": "Adjectives with two syllables lose the vowel of the second syllable when they gain a suffix, so 'lytel' becomes 'lytle' when it gains the singular nominative neuter suffix 'e'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "On þissum geare sende he þone (<em>eald</em>) #### biscop Wulfstan to þæm stede þe wæs genemned Readingum⁠ — In this year he sent the old bishop to the place that was called Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "ealdan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eald' is modifying the singular accusative masculine 'biscop' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "",
                "explanation": ""
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He sende þæt (<em>halig</em>) #### lic to þæm mynster⁠ — He sent the holy body to the minster",
        "correctAnswer": "halge",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' is modifying the singular accusative neuter 'lic' so it takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "halgan",
                "explanation": "An adjective takes the gender of its noun. As can be seen by 'þæt', 'lic' is neuter so 'halig' should take the neuter accusative 'e' ending"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "halige",
                "explanation": "While the suffix is correct, adjectives with two syllables lose the vowel of the second syllable when they gain a suffix, so 'halig' becomes 'halge' when it gains the singular accusative neuter suffix 'e'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se ðe gebigde ðone (<em>heah</em>) #### heofonlican bigels⁠ — He who bowed the high vault of heaven",
        "correctAnswer": "heagan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heah' is modifying the singular accusative masculine 'bigels' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "heahan",
                "explanation": "Words ending in 'h' replace their 'h' with a 'g' before a suffix beginning with a vowel, so 'heah' becomes 'heagan' when it gains the ending 'an'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se deofol gesette hine uppan ðam scylfe ðæs (<em>heah</em>) #### temples⁠ — The devil set him upon the summit of the high temple",
        "correctAnswer": "heagan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heah' is modifying the singular genitive masculine 'temple' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "heahan",
                "explanation": "Words ending in 'h' replace their 'h' with a 'g' before a suffix beginning with a vowel, so 'heah' becomes 'heagan' when it gains the ending 'an'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He is in ðone deopan grund ðæs hatan leges and ðæs (<em>heard</em>) #### leges⁠ — He is in the deep abyss of the hot flame and the hard flame ",
        "correctAnswer": "heardan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' is modifying the singular genitive masculine 'leg' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hwæt synt nu þæs foremeran ond þæs (<em>wis</em>) #### goldsmiðes ban Welondes?⁠ — What now are the bones of that renowned and wise goldsmith Weland?",
        "correctAnswer": "wisan",
        "explanation":"Here 'wis' is modifying the singular genitive masculine 'goldsmiðes' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða wicingas eodon þa to þære (<em>lytel</em>) #### iege þe is genemned Iona⁠ — The vikings then went to the little island that is named Iona",
        "correctAnswer": "lytlan",
        "explanation":"Here 'lytel' is modifying the singular dative feminine 'ieg' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "lytelan",
                "explanation": "While the suffix is correct, adjectives with two syllables lose the vowel of the second syllable when they gain a suffix, so 'lytel' becomes 'lytlan' when it gains the singular genitive feminine suffix 'an'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Woroldlicra weorca on ðam (<em>halig</em>) #### dæge geswice man georne⁠ — On that holy day, let men abstain from worldly works",
        "correctAnswer": "halgan",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' is modifying the singular dative masculine 'dæg' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "haligan",
                "explanation": "While the suffix is correct, adjectives with two syllables lose the vowel of the second syllable when they gain a suffix, so 'halig' becomes 'halgan' when it gains the singular dative masculine suffix 'an'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ðe hæbbe aþriet mid ðis (<em>lang</em>) #### spelle⁠ — I have bored you with this long speech",
        "correctAnswer": "langan",
        "explanation":"Here 'lang' is modifying the singular dative neuter 'spell' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ac uton don swa swa God tæhte þæt ure (<em>god</em) #### weorc beon on ða wisan mannum cuðe⁠ — But let us do as God has taught, that our good works may be so known to men",
        "correctAnswer": "godan",
        "explanation":"Here 'god' is modifying the plural nominative neuter 'weorc' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða (<em>heard</em>) #### þrowunga ðe he adreag⁠ — The hard sufferings than he endured",
        "correctAnswer": "heardan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' is modifying the plural nominative feminine 'þrowunga' so it takes the 'an' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða (<em>eald</em>) #### wunde spræce þa ealdan race⁠ — The old wounds speak the old stories",
        "correctAnswer": "ealdan",
        "explanation":"Here 'eald' is modifying the plural nominative feminine 'racu' so it takes the 'an' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>eald</em>) #### wif scielde þæt bearn mid hire lice⁠ — An old woman shielded the child with her body",
        "correctAnswer": "eald",
        "explanation":"Here 'eald' is modifying the singular nominative neuter 'wif' so it takes no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Lucia to manegum witum geworht be (<em>yfel</em>) #### man⁠ — Lucia was put to many tortures by an evil man",
        "correctAnswer": "yfel",
        "explanation":"Here 'yfel' is modifying the singular nominative masculine 'man' so it takes no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>halig</em>) #### abbod nerede ða hæðenan cyningas⁠ — A holy bishop saved the heathen kings",
        "correctAnswer": "halig",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' is modifying the singular nominative masculine 'man' so it takes no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On Æþelredes cyninges dagum, timbrode seo fierd (<em>micel</em>) #### mynster⁠ — In King Ethelred's day, the army built a great monastery",
        "correctAnswer": "micel",
        "explanation":"Here 'micel' is modifying the singular accusative neuter 'mynster' so it takes no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Harold cyning þis gehierde þa gaderode he (<em>micel</em>) #### fierd⁠ — King Harold heard this, then he gathered a large army",
        "correctAnswer": "micele",
        "explanation":"Here 'micel' is modifying the singular accusative feminine 'fierd' so it takes the 'e' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cnapa huntode (<em>æðele</em>) #### hwæl⁠ — The boy hunts a noble whale",
        "correctAnswer": "æðelne",
        "explanation":"Here 'æðele' is modifying the singular accusative masculine 'hwæl' so it takes the 'ne' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "She wæs (<em>æðele</em>) #### gebyrde⁠ — She was of noble birth",
        "correctAnswer": "æðelre",
        "explanation":"Here 'æðele' is modifying the singular genitive feminine 'byrd' so it takes the 're' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Buteran ond beana ond ealle clæne þingc ic ete mid (<em>micel</em>) #### þancunge⁠ — Butter and beans and all clean things I eat with many thanks",
        "correctAnswer": "micelre ",
        "explanation":"Here 'micel' is modifying the singular genitive feminine 'þancung' so it takes the 're' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic fliemde þa wealas to (<em>weste</em>) #### iege⁠ — I expelled the foreigners to a deserted island",
        "correctAnswer": "westre",
        "explanation":"Here 'weste' is modifying the singular dative feminine 'ieg' so it takes the 're' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic hafu gecnawen on (<em>heard</em>) #### hyge ðæt ðu hælend eart middangeardes⁠ — I have acknowledged in my hard heart that you are saviour of the world",
        "correctAnswer": "heardum",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' is modifying the singular dative masculine 'hyge' so it takes the 'um' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We rædaþ ond hieraþ word be Æþelrede cyning, be (<em>eald</em>) #### weale, and be þæm gefeohtum⁠ — We read and hear words about King Ethelred, about old wealth and about the fights",
        "correctAnswer": "ealdum ",
        "explanation":"Here 'eald' is modifying the singular dative masculine 'weala' so it takes the 'um' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>wis</em>) #### men onfeng þone anhaga⁠ — Wise men received the wanderer",
        "correctAnswer": "wise",
        "explanation":"Here 'wis' is modifying the plural nominative masculine 'man' so it takes the 'e' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>geong</em>) #### preostas mette þæs cyninges bearn⁠ — Young priests met the king's children",
        "correctAnswer": "geonge",
        "explanation":"Here 'geong' is modifying the plural nominative masculine 'preost' so it takes the 'e' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>god</em>) #### sawla sint undeaþlice and ece⁠ — Good souls are immortal and eternal",
        "correctAnswer": "goda",
        "explanation":"Here 'god' is modifying the plural nominative feminine 'sawel' so it takes the 'a' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Næs þes þegn þa unwise þa he sende (<em>eald</em>) #### scipu to þa wealum⁠ — Is this thane not then unwise when he sent old ships to the foreigners",
        "correctAnswer": "ealde",
        "explanation":"Here 'eald' is modifying the plural accusative neuter 'scip' so it takes the 'e' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se abbod wæs eald, ac he lærde (<em>geong</em>) #### preostas mid wisum wordum⁠ — The abbod was old but he instructed young priests with wise words",
        "correctAnswer": "geonge",
        "explanation":"Here 'geong' is modifying the plural accusative masculine 'preost' so it takes the 'e' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ælfred cyning gefeaht wið feower sciphlæstas (<em>Denisc</em>) #### monna here⁠ — King Alfred fought with four crews of Danish men here",
        "correctAnswer": "Deniscra",
        "explanation":"Here 'Denisc' is modifying the plural genitive masculine 'man' so it takes the 'ra' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wæs he swiðe æþelra gebyrda ond (<em>god</em>) ####⁠ — He was of very noble and good birth",
        "correctAnswer": "godra",
        "explanation":"Here 'god' is modifying the plural genitive feminine 'byrd' so it takes the 'ra' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Win nys drenc cilda ac ealdra ond (<em>wis</em>) #### men- Wine is not a drink of children, but of old and wise men",
        "correctAnswer": "wisra",
        "explanation":"Here 'wis' is modifying the plural genitive masculine 'man' so it takes the 'ra' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On ælcum þingum ðe ðær unbecweden biþ on bocum and on swylcum (<em>lytel</em>) #### þingum⁠ — On all things that are unbequeathed, books and other such little things",
        "correctAnswer": "lytlum",
        "explanation":"Here 'lytel' is modifying the plural dative neuter 'þing' so it takes the 'um' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Dunstan wæs unwise and he befæstte þæt land to (<em>geong</em>) #### preostum⁠ — Dunstan was unwise and he commited that land to young priests",
        "correctAnswer": "geongum",
        "explanation":"Here 'geong' is modifying the plural dative masculine 'preost' so it takes the 'um' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie eodon fram Norwege mid (<em>micel</em>) #### scipfierde⁠ — They came from Norway with a large navy",
        "correctAnswer": "miclum",
        "explanation":"Here 'micel' is modifying the plural dative feminine 'scipfierd' so it takes the 'um' suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He is (<em>strang</em>) #### ðonne ic⁠ — He is stronger than I",
        "correctAnswer": "strengra",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'strang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'streng', but it isn't modifying a noun so it takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'strengra'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "strengran",
                "explanation": "Comparatives only decline if they are modifying a noun. This adjective is not modifying a noun, so it becomes 'strengra'"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "strangra",
                "explanation": "The stem of 'strang' undergoes 'i-mutation' so the 'a' becomes 'e', meaning 'strang' becomes 'strengra' in the comparative"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Bebead he ðæt him mon (<em>lang</em>) #### cwidas beforan cwæde, and he symle gedefelice æftercwæþ⁠ — He ordered longer sayings to be spoken before him, and he always repeated them properly",
        "correctAnswer": "lengran",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'lengran' as comparatives decline weak if they are modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "langran",
                "explanation": "The stem of 'lang' undergoes 'i-mutation' so the 'a' becomes 'e', meaning 'lang' becomes 'lengran' in the comparative"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "lengra",
                "explanation":"Here 'lang' takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'lengran' as comparatives decline weak if they are modifying a noun"
            },
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "langra",
                "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the 'ran' suffix to become 'lengran' as comparatives decline weak if they are modifying a noun"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic in wite sceal bidan in bendum ond me (<em>god</em>) #### ham for oferhygdum æfre ne wene⁠ — I must in tormen abide in bonds, and never hope for any better home for my pride",
        "correctAnswer": "beteran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'god' is irregular and so becomes 'beteran' in the comparative when modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se horshwæl biþ micle (<em>lytel</em>) #### ðonne oðre hwalas⁠ — The walrus is much smaller than other whales",
        "correctAnswer": "læssa",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'lytel' is irregular and so becomes 'læssa' in the comparative when not modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic towurpe mine bernu and ic wyrce (<em>micel</em>) #### bernu⁠ — I will tear down my barns and I will build bigger barns",
        "correctAnswer": "maran",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular and so becomes 'maran' in the comparative when modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt læstede þa xix wintra þa hwile þe Stephne cyning wæs one æfre hit wæs (<em>yfel</em>) #### ond wiersa⁠ — That lasted 19 winters while Stephen was king and ever it was worse and worse",
        "correctAnswer": "wiersa",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'yfel' is irregular and so becomes 'wiersa' in the comparative as it is not modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Næfre he ær ne siððan (<em>heard</em>) #### hæle fand⁠ — Never before or since did he find a stouter warrior",
        "correctAnswer": "heardran",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the 'ran' suffix as it is modifying the noun 'hæle'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wisa, hwilc cræft þe geþuht betwux þas (<em>furðre</em>) #### wesan⁠ — Teacher, which craft do you think is the greater?",
        "correctAnswer": "furþra|furðra",
        "explanation":"Here 'furðre' loses its 're' and takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'furðra', as it is not modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se wudu is eastlang and westlang hund twelftiges mila lang oððe (<em>lang</em>) ####⁠ — The wood, from east to west, is twelve hundred miles long or longer",
        "correctAnswer": "lengra",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'lang' undergoes i-mutation to become 'leng', and it takes the 'ra' suffix to become 'lengra', as it is not directly modifying a noun",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðam (<em>mild</em>) #### cyninge Wihtræde rixigendum⁠ — In the reign of the kindest king Wihtræd",
        "correctAnswer": "mildostan",
        "explanation":"Here 'mild' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the weak suffix 'an', as it comes after the definitive article 'þam' ",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se lichoma ðonne on ðone (<em>heard</em>) #### stenc and on ðone fulostan biþ gecyrred⁠ — The body then shall be turned to the strongest and foulest stench",
        "correctAnswer": "heardostan",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the weak suffix 'an', as it comes after the definitive article 'ðone'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Cwædon ðæt he wære manna (<em>mild</em>) #### and monþwærost⁠ — They said that he was kindest and most courteous of men",
        "correctAnswer": "mildost",
        "explanation":"Here 'heard' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He sohte fram ðam ieldestan oþ ðone (<em>geong</em>) ####⁠ — He searched from the eldest to the youngest",
        "correctAnswer": "gingestan",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'geong' undergoes i-mutation to become 'ging', and takes the superlative suffix 'est' and the weak suffix 'an', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'ðone'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic gyrne fultum ðinre foreþingrædene ðu (<em>halig</em>) #### mægden and þrowystr⁠ — I earnestly impolore your help, you holiest maiden and martyr",
        "correctAnswer": "haligoste",
        "explanation":"Here 'halig' takes the superlative suffix 'ost' and the strong accusative feminine suffix 'e' as it is modifying 'mægden'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se wæs on lare and on dæde se (<em>heah</em>) ####⁠ — He was in learning and in deed the highest",
        "correctAnswer": "hiehsta",
        "explanation":"The stem of 'heah' undergoes i-mutation to become 'hieh', and takes the superlative suffix 'st' and the weak nominative masculine suffix 'a', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'se'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "hiehost|hiehest",
                "explanation":"Because 'heah' ends in a 'h', it drops the vowel in 'ost' to take the superlative suffix 'st'. Since it modifies a weak nominative masculine noun, it also takes the suffix 'a'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He me sealde ðæt (<em>god</em>) #### hors⁠ — He gave me the best horse",
        "correctAnswer": "betest",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'god' is irregular, becoming 'betest' in the superlative. It takes no suffix because 'hors' is neuter and neuter accusative nouns have no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sceall beon se (<em>lytel</em>) #### dæl nyhst þæm tune ðe se deada man on lið⁠ — The smallest portion shall be closest to where the dead man lies",
        "correctAnswer": "læsta",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'lytel' is irregular, becoming 'læst' in the superlative. It takes the weak nominative masculine ending 'a' to become 'læsta', as it comes after the demonstrative pronoun 'se'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hit is ealra wyrta (<em>micel</em>) ####⁠ — It is greatest of all herbs",
        "correctAnswer": "mæst",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'micel' is irregular, becoming 'mæst' in the superlative. It takes no suffix",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se deofol sloh lob mid ðære (<em>yfel</em>) #### wunde⁠ — The devil slew Job with the worst of wounds",
        "correctAnswer": "wierstan",
        "explanation":"The adjective 'yfel' is irregular, becoming 'wierst' in the superlative. It takes the weak genitive feminine ending 'an' to become 'wierstan'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]